[Music]
hello everyone welcome to the 42nd live
episode of ask a budget
as you know today we discuss science
astrophysics and technology and all that
so let us see who all we have with us i
can see somnath parth yash dungar singh
johan
pinky kumari abhijit nair ojaswa ananta
arpan
gorav aryan devi gurav parshuram
neha
anthony
and so many other people gaurav niraj
kumar singh prithviram
good evening good day to everybody great
to be with you great to see you all
thank you for being here
and let's get into it with question
number one
so
question number one is by churching
why does the earth spin
and can we send humans to venus
so to understand why the earth spins why
other planets spin and why does the
solar system spin etc we have to
understand
how the solar system was formed
so the solar system was formed
uh several billion years ago from a
large from an enormous cloud
of gas
and this cloud of gas started uh
spinning around its overall center of
mass slowly over the millions and
billions of years
started spinning around and parts of it
started coalescing together in these
were the uh seeds of the future planets
of the solar system and at the center of
this enormous whirling cloud of gas
you had
a big concentration of of gas and other
material around the center of mass which
became eventually our star the sun
and once it had sufficient mass it was
able to ignite nuclear fusion within
itself so that is how the solar system
formed it's formed out of an enormous
spinning cloud of gas
and these local coalescences of mass
also were spinning from the very
beginning that's how gravity happens
that's of gravity works when there is a
concentration of mass in any place it
attracts other mass towards itself
and that always goes in the form of a
spinning uh formation right
so everything was spinning from the very
beginning
and that is why the earth spins because
after everything cooled down and after
all these billions of years that
original rotational motion still
persists because of the force of in
because of the law of inertia and all
that
so that is the reason why the earth
spins the moon spins the planets revolve
around the sun the sun itself spins
the solar system the entire uh solar
system itself spins revolves around the
sun
and it's why the galaxy itself or milky
way galaxy itself
spins
and our sun goes around the center of
mass of the galaxy
so this is the reason why the earth
spins it is the inherent uh
it's it's what comes out
of the force of gravity the force of
gravity causes
such
accumulations and concentrations of
masses to spin around the center of mass
so that is why
this phenomenon
is observed this is why it occurs now
can we send humans to venus
it is possible to send humans to venus
we have the technological capability the
know how to do that we have chemical
rockets which would take a few months to
reach venus
and it is certainly possible it is not
beyond our capability to ensure that
a human being or a number of human
beings could be transported there
safely and even brought back safely the
question is
can humans
live on ma on venus and can humans
even go to the surface of the planet and
come back
safely
and as of today that is almost
impossible because the conditions on the
planet are quite hellish
the atmospheric pressure on the surface
of venus is
several hundred times the atmospheric
pressure on the earth i think it's
around 300 times earth's atmospheric
pressure if i'm not mistaken
and the temperature is also very very
high
it's like in the hundreds of degrees
centigrade
so it is so hot and so um
and the pressure is so high that you a
metal like lead would probably melt on
the surface of the planet
so it's it's not possible to send humans
to the surface of venus as of today we
can certainly send humans in orbit
around venus and most likely bring them
back safely so that is what we can
achieve as of today
venus is of course quite close to the
earth that's why it is possible to send
humans to the planet have a few orbits
done there and then maybe bring them
back that's what we can achieve as of
today
question two
by ajay
do you think the coronavirus is
engineered perfectly so that it can
attack people only with certain dna
because
we don't see the delta strain in
pakistan or china but you see it in
india or in the us
well you are right your observation is
right it does seem to be well somehow
targeted uh geographically somehow
because certain stains strains are
seen they are prevalent in certain
countries in certain geographical
regions
for example if you look at india you
have the delta strain if you look at the
us you're the delta strain but if you
cross over the border to pakistan you
don't see this
i mean there's not much of a problem
there if you cross over to bangladesh
you don't see it if you cross over sri
lanka you don't see much of an issue as
far as i know i am not really being been
tracking the situation in sri lanka but
as far as i know
there doesn't seem to be much of an
issue there the way we have it in india
again crossover to burma cross over to
tibet there's not much of an issue
so it's clear that it seems to be
targeted into the
at the geography of india again the same
thing with the united states in the past
we had certain places like uh certain
nations in uh in europe for example
italy
and in france and the uk where you had a
very high mortality rate more than 10
percent of the of the infected people
were dying in the beginning in the first
quarter the first half of 2020 if i
recall correctly
and the same thing wasn't seen anywhere
else so
it is quite apparent quite obvious that
there does seem to be some kind of
targeting of certain populations of
certain geographical regions
at certain times
and that does give the impression that
this is an engineered
virus and the whoever is
tinkering with the genetic makeup of
this virus seems to have found some way
of
specifically targeting certain
ethnicities or certain geographies or
certain uh
certain
population groups with
with a certain kind of dna apparently it
does look like it is that way so yes it
is uh
it is in my opinion quite likely that
this could be a bioengineered virus and
new strains come out from time to time
you have the first wave in the second
wave now they are talking about a third
wave
right they're already talking about the
third wave a third wave in autumn of
this year right now we're in september
autumn is like october onwards october
november those two two three months
so are talking about a third wave and
maybe some new strain
so it's like
it's like someone's releasing these
these various
strains of the virus these mutated new
mutated forms of the virus it looks like
that of course we do know that viruses
mutate on their own that is well known
but then if they mutate they would not
target specific
geographies or specific populations
selectively so that is what makes it
look very curious and very fishy
so i agree this is very curious and it
doesn't seem to be a natural phenomenon
ritesh asks till well till when can we
expect this
disgusting kovad time to end
it's been
two years now and this terror doesn't
end
well i had the
i had said this a few months ago i think
in in ranveer's show that this is going
to be the decade of the virus
it's not ending anytime soon new strains
new variants of the virus
are coming out every few months
and
you know it's it's like it's a
never-ending cycle we thought that 2020
was the bad year well 2021 is just the
same
and even in populations in countries
that are almost like with the majority
of the people are vaccinated you're
still seeing
the virus affecting people it's as if
the vaccine
well it's it's pointless almost like
that so take some countries for example
israel israel i think more than half the
people have been vaccinated by now
maybe 70 if i am if i recall correctly
i'm not very sure and yet you have this
big problem of people falling ill
because of the virus
so it looks like you need one dose then
you need another dose of the vaccine now
there is talk of certain vaccines having
three doses now there are certain
companies that are going to offer
uh
pills that you have to ingest twice a
day
in addition to taking the vaccine
it's like a never-ending cycle so it
looks like there'll be more and more
strains that come out and as long as the
virus exists we have to be under
lockdown forever essentially so it looks
like this is going to be the decade of
the virus
and
so whom does the virus benefit it does
benefit pharmaceutical companies western
pharmaceutical companies who sell
vaccines for profit so one dose is not
enough sell two doses if two doses you
want to make some more money sell the
third dose as well make it mandatory
make the politicians ensure that the
people have to take three doses
otherwise they are not allowed to go
anywhere you know and politicians the
world over whether it's in north america
whether it's europe whether it's
australia whether it's asia politicians
the world or the same kind of people
they love power they are power hungry
people they are money hungry people the
majority of politicians i'm not saying
all politicians are like that but the
majority of politicians we know how they
are the the entire world over they love
power as of today they have gained so
much power over the people of the of the
world
they can ask people to stay indoors they
can ask people to wear mars they can ask
people to dance around in circles and
people will have to do it
right so this is the kind of power they
have not had for uh for centuries
for at least a century
and politicians are power hungry they
don't want to give this power up so now
that they have this power to mandate all
kinds of nonsense
they will be very loath to give it up
so they
may keep on ensuring that something or
the other goes wrong and we have to stay
indoors we have to stay under lockdown
various forms of lockdown arbitrary
lockdowns whenever they want
and just keep on making the world dance
at the to the tunes that's what most
politicians love and that could be one
factor apart from the pharmaceutical
industry factor that ensures that for
many years to come we will be under some
form of lockdown
so i don't see
this
this age of the virus to end any time so
i don't see it ending anytime soon i
think this entire decade is going to be
like that and perhaps the world has
changed forever we will never have the
freedoms perhaps
that we had until
until 2020. you know those freedoms may
be a thing of the past
vaccine passports may become mandatory
you will not be allowed to go to a
cinema hall unless you're vaccinated
unless you had your two or three doses
of the vaccine and you've paid for that
you may not be allowed to go to
restaurants you may not be able to allow
to get on a plane you may not be allowed
you may not get a visa for another
country unless you are you demonstrate
that you have taken the vaccine and
maybe the indian vaccine won't be
allowed you have to take the some other
vaccine which they like you know which
brings them money so that's the kind of
nonsensical era we have entered
you know
everything is commercialized
everything is monetized
and uh so so that's where we are today i
don't see this ending anytime soon this
may be the entire decade of the vaccine
unfortunately
avinash says if humans evolved from
monkeys
why do monkeys still exist
well i think it's a good question it's a
good question
it's a logical question it's a good
question so so let's let's take a
broader look at the world
tigers
evolved from cats from ancient cats
but other cats do exist
lions
evolved from cats ancient cats but other
cats do exist we have cheetahs we have
leopards we have bobcats we have lynxes
we have pumas
we have the clouded leopard the spotted
leopard the amur leopard
we have the house cat we have various
species of wild cats
right so we have so many species of cats
and yet the most evolved the strongest
ones are the lions and the tigers
it's because there have been many
species of cats over the
past millions of years
let's look let's take a look at the dog
the
the dog the domesticated dog is a
subspecies of the wolf
so these dogs and wolves they are the
same species essentially they evolve
from ancient
canine species but you do have foxes you
do have jackals
you also have bears who are closely
related to dogs you also have seals and
you also have the baleen whales and the
porpoises and dolphins who are all part
of the broader family
so there have been several species of
the same family
of animals
out of which dogs have evolved
right
now when it comes to dolphins
we have dolphins a regular
common dolphin bottled nose dolphin but
we also have the orcas the killer whales
which are the largest species of dolphin
we also have other species of dolphin we
have the gangetic dolphin we have the
iravati dolphin
and we have various
several species of dolphin
so so the dolphin the regular common
dolphin is supposed to be the second
most intelligent animal that we know of
after us
so they evolved from ancient dolphins so
why do why are there so many other
species of dolphins
it's because there have always been many
species of dolphins and one of these
species happen to be happens to be the
most evolved today
similarly
in the past there have been several
species of monkeys and apes
and the most intelligent one of those
today is us
we are the most intelligent monkey or
ape today it doesn't mean that there
should be no other monkeys or apes right
so that's how it is it's always been
like that there are there has been this
parallel evolution many parts of
evolution of closely related
species of animals
right families of animals
i think a family has a number of species
within it and so on and so forth
so that's how it is that's why that's
how the evolution works it happens in
parallel you want it's not linear
of course it is linear if you trace back
our own ancestry but then if you go back
several million years it converges with
the uh lineages of other species as well
so that's how it goes
aniket says what if we use 100 of our
brain some science fiction movies claim
that we will be able to use our psychic
powers and time travel and control
everything just like being a god please
answer
see we have to understand that science
fiction is mostly entertainment
it's about entertaining the masters it's
about entertaining the audience not all
science fiction is hard science there is
a category of science fiction called
hard science fiction and then there is
all the other science fiction and in
bookstores science fiction and fantasy
is always together so fantasy is not
even science
but
but many people believe that fantasy and
science fiction are the same thing
so
the thing is this that uh
we most likely do use 100 percent of our
brain
our brain has a it's it's a large thing
it's a large
organ
it's the most energy intensive energy
hungry organ in the body
as far as i know yeah
now
we don't understand how the brain works
we know very little about the brain we
low we know maybe two or three percent
of how the brain actually works we know
what is the internal structure of the
brain because we have been dissecting
brains for the past few hundred years we
know how it is inside we know what is
the neural structure to some extent
right ganglions and dendrites and
clusters of neurons and it's most likely
the connections between these neurons
that produce memories then the question
arises of consciousness what is
consciousness and so on we know that
there is an internal brain the reptilian
brain then there is an external exterior
brain and so on and so forth
and all of these various regions and
parts of the brain have their own
functionality they have their own use
they have their own function
and they do fulfill the function see
nature is parsimonious
evolution ensures that there is no
nothing extraneous in an organ which is
not needed because anything that's
extraneous
is a burden to an organism and it will
ensure that it gets weeded out in the
survival of the fetus of the fittest
so everything is well designed it has
evolved over millions of years
and every part of our brain is actually
functional it has some use it has some
function it's it has a purpose that it
does serve we don't understand what
these purposes are we don't understand
what the various parts of the brain do
it doesn't mean that we don't use 100 of
the brain
so that is something we have to
understand science fiction is mostly
entertainment
and some people talk about hacking the
brain and trying to overclock the brain
inject data into the brain see we don't
understand how the brain works and if
you start fiddling with the
with the core functionality of the brain
it's going to cause problems in whoever
brain whichever person's brain you do
these experiments it can even cause
someone to go insane who knows what's
going to happen
right we don't know
why we sleep
what is the use of sleep i mean almost
every organism
on the planet has some form of sleep
especially uh
multicellular organisms and organisms
that have uh significant brains
so
so sleep does seem to have some function
but we don't know what it is
now one of the ways people talk about of
hacking the brain or using more of the
brain is by trying to eliminate the need
for sleep
well we it has been observed then when
that when an organism is deprived of
sleep over a period of seven eight ten
days
it inevitably leads to death
right the the animal or whoever it is
dies if this is done
and therefore you are trying to do
something that is highly unnatural
so my point is that we don't really
understand how the brain works
it is a very popular myth and with
misconception because of science fiction
movies and fantasy movies that we only
use maybe one percent or two percent of
the brain if we take some super drug
then we will start to use all
everything else
and it may give us super human power
that is a very dangerous myth it should
not be taken seriously it's good for
science fiction and fantasy movies but
that's not the real world
so that's
the answer to this question
akash says why do stars which are
situated far from the center of the
galaxy
revolve faster or at least as fast as a
star which is closer to the center
because this doesn't work
in the solar system
mercury revolves another around the sun
faster than pluto
but this doesn't happen at the galactic
level why is that this is a very good
question
so here's what it is see
uh
the solar system
or if you look at the solar system if
you look at the mass composition of the
solar system
more than 99.8
of the mass
of the entire solar system
is just the sun
so the sun itself all by itself makes up
more than 99.8 percent of the mass of
the entire solar system
now when you have
a planet
going around
let's say the sun
in orbit
so it's it's orbital motion
then what happens is that uh
what happens is that the centripetal
force and the centripetal acceleration
and gravitational acceleration have to
balance out to maintain the planet in
orbit it also works when you have a
satellite in orbit around the earth
and
it all depends the speed
of the orbit the orbital velocity
depends on two factors
three factors but if the if the main
object is very massive then you can just
take two factors one is the mass of the
object that is being revolved around and
secondly the distance
of
your planet from the sun let's say okay
so in the case of the solar system as we
go closer to the sun orbital speed
gets it rises the orbital velocity right
it gets higher faster and faster that's
why mercury venus earth mars have high
orbital velocities whereas uranus
neptune pluto etc have very low orbital
velocities because you have the same
mass that they are revolving around
now when it comes to the galaxy
you have a supermassive black hole at
the center of the galaxy
but as you go further and further away
from the center of the galaxy the mass
of the galaxy
increases
right because the galaxy is a big
diffuse object
in the case of the solar system most of
the mass more than 99.8 of the mass is
right at the center so no matter how far
or close you go you're always orbiting
the same amount of mass
but in the case of a galaxy as we go
further and further away from the center
you're orbiting a more and more massive
thing
because if you look at the
uh
radius
of your orbit here there is more mass as
you go outwards that you are orbiting
and that is the reason why because the
mass increases this uh
the the speed of the of the orbit also
increases and this is what we see in the
galactic rotation curves let me uh
let me share that image
so this is a galactic rotation curve
so you can see that as the distance from
the center of the galaxy see over here
you can see the center of the galaxy if
you can
see my mouse pointer over here is the
center of the galaxy as you go further
and further away from the center of the
galaxy
the speed of rotation of stars
increases whereas it is supposed to
decrease or or you know
if if all the mass was in just one place
at the center
it was suppose it was supposed to
decrease
and that this this phenomenon is
observed because of the
of the presence of dark matter
the galaxy has a very sizable dark
matter hello
i think
the diameter of the dark matter hello is
about 2 million light years which is
enormous
so as you go further from the center of
the galaxy there is more and more mass
that you are
revolving around
and that is why
the speed increases as you go further
instead of decreasing if all the mass
was just concentrated at the center
it's a reasonably technical thing to
understand but it's uh so so that's how
it goes if you understand what orbits
are made up of and what is the physics
behind orbits then you will
figure this out
aniket says what's your opinion about
elon musk do you think he is some kind
of revolutionaries revolutionizer
or something
in my opinion he is very overrated he is
a great businessman that's it he isn't a
scientist
as he portrays himself
tesla wasn't founded by him neither was
paypal so what actually his contribution
in the field of science and technology
so listen i haven't really studied the
history of tesla or paypal so i don't
know who founded it uh
that doesn't really matter so so
as far as i know
elon musk has
degrees in physics
i think bachelor of masters degrees i
think at least bachelor's degrees and if
i recall correctly he was
he did get get admission to a phd
program one of the one of the major uh
us universities i think it was cornell
if i'm not mistaken he
got into the phd program in physics
in one of the major us universities and
he chose to drop out of it so he is
clearly good enough he was clearly good
enough to get admission
as a phd candidate in a top us
university
now i am sure he doesn't have a phd
degree so what is the definition of a
scientist
are you a scientist if you have a degree
like if you have a master's degree in in
physics does it make you a scientist or
do you need to have a degree like a phd
degree
in physics to be a scientist
is the degree all that matters to be a
scientist there are thousands tens of
thousands maybe millions of phd holders
in this country in india
who are not scientists
they haven't produced a single original
scientific discovery or anything at all
so having a degree of some kind doesn't
make you a scientist i know elon musk
doesn't have a phd
does it
mean that he is not a scientist
and many of these phd degree holders who
are officially scientists in the eyes of
the world
what do they do what do they contribute
to society
they they
write research papers
which are published in obscure journals
that nobody reads
the only people who read these papers
are other scientists that's a very small
community and more than 99 of these
papers will have no real impact on the
world they will not make any great
change in the world
it's like you know there's this uh
saying in in science in academia publish
or perish so if you want to keep
progressing or in rising riding
and climbing the academic ladder you
have to keep publishing research papers
every year or number of papers every
year four or five
at least per year at least three i would
say
and that ensures that you keep uh
climbing the academic ladder you get
promotions and you eventually get tenure
but what difference does it make to the
world what good that is does it do to
the world these people are officially
scientists in the eyes of the world they
have a position they have a degree
but if you look at the history of the
past 40 years there's not been one
single new discovery
in physics
that throws new light upon the universe
as we understand as you see it
physics has not progressed in the past
40 years
so what is the point of having these
degrees and having these academicians
and all that what good are they doing to
the world that's my question i'm not
saying elon musk is good or something i
am saying what is the meaning what is
the definition of a scientist
what's the definition of an intellectual
an intellectual is somebody who produces
new ideas
it's not somebody who reads hundreds of
books i have all these books behind me
does it mean i'm an intellectual
i am not an intellectual if i read 500
books or a thousand books there are
people who say i read 50 books a year so
i'm an intellectual
an intellectual is a person
who produces genuine new ideas that are
actually useful to society
that actually takes society forwards
there are many people who produce these
garbage ideas who produce research
papers who publish books that make no
difference in the world it's just the
regurgitation and rehashing of old ideas
so publishing a book doesn't make you a
scientist or an intellectual
publishing research papers
that are worthless doesn't make you a
scientist or an intellectual reading 5
000 books doesn't make you an
intellectual or a scientist a scientist
is somebody
who produces genuine new ideas and
brings the word world forward
now what does elon musk do
he is definitely a businessman he wanted
to be a physicist he
went for a phd into in physics and then
he abandoned it because most likely he
did not like the academic environment
and
he sought to succeed in this adopted
country of his adoptive country office
the united states and as a businessman
to succeed in the u.s you have to well
play by certain rules
and he found a way of succeeding at that
he is definitely a great businessman he
is not a scientist i agree because he is
not doing any research he is
uh
trying to find ways of sending humans to
mars
he is of course putting all this
all these satellite constellations in
space iridium i think
yeah
so yeah he is doing all that he he does
not fit my definition of a scientist but
he's clearly a visionary
of course all
all his work is going to benefit him
it's going to enrich him
so if you think that is bad well then
that's not a very good thing
i would say that
any
progress in business any progress in
science should benefit the whole of
humanity
but the us the american capitalistic
system is not like that everything
is monetized even vaccines are monetized
any scientific invention is used to make
money for a very small number of people
and that's just the way the system is so
he wanted to succeed in that country
because there was nothing for him in
south africa this is there was no
entrepreneurial entrepreneurial
environment there so he chose to come to
the us he chose to try and succeed there
he has succeeded so there is his
contribution to the world
he will
most he will
possibly succeed in sending humans to
mars i
suppose in the next 10 20 years
whom will it benefit it will benefit a
small number of people it's not going to
be used for the benefit of humanity it's
going to be used well to enrich him his
company his shareholders take holders
and so on that's just how the game is
played
so that's about him i don't see him as a
bad person i don't see him as somebody
who is evil i think he's better in some
ways than many other business people
he's not a scientist he has chosen not
to be a scientist he was clearly good
enough to be one at least by the
academic standards he would he would
have gotten himself a phd and he would
have maybe published a bunch of research
papers but that's not what makes a
scientist
so all in all that's about elon musk i
don't see him as an evil person i see
the system
well
i am saying this this capitalistic
system is evil it does not mean i'm a
marxist or a socialist uh marxism and
socialism is equally if not more evil
than capitalism
but that's just the way the world is
you know i have spoken about geopolitics
in the past it's all about conquering
the world
and it's all about pursuing your
personal interests
selfishly
well so is the capitalistic system
that's also the way it is you know
so he has found a way to succeed in that
and it's good for
him okay
says do you think humans will
survive a mass extinction or will we go
on like this forever so will humanity is
humanity in a position
to survive a mass extinction or will
humanity last forever
well you know what nothing lasts forever
we have had many species of human beings
in the past that have disappeared
we are a relatively new species of human
being we have been around for a quarter
million years in the anatomically modern
form
homo sapiens
now
are we in a position that we can survive
a mass extinction so what's a mass
extinction it's a catastrophic event of
some kind
in which
a majority of the living beings and
species on the planet go extinct
so that could be something like an
asteroid strike or a comet strike
like what happened about 65 million
years ago in the
uh czech retreat impact event which uh
what was what killed of the majority of
the dinosaurs some dinosaurs did survive
and our ancestors
who were very small at the time
they also did survive that so they did
survive the mass extinction that is that
killed off the majority of the known
avian dinosaurs
right so that is one mass extinction our
ancestors survived
now
are we in a position
to survive another such mass extinction
what if a comet were to impact the
planet i don't see humanity surviving
that
we can try and
nudge the comet out of its orbit that it
that will coincide with the earth's
orbit that we can do if we can see it
coming
with sufficient time in hand
we can
we may be able to deflect an asteroid
and nudge it out of the way if it is
coming towards earth but if it is too
late and if it if it does impact the
earth then there's no way humanity can
survive we will go the way of the
dinosaurs now there are other ways of
having a mass extinction for example
right now we are destroying the oceans
we are polluting the oceans we are
choking the oceans with plastic
and we are dumping all kinds of
chemicals and other things into the
ocean
in the past there have been a mass
extinction events that saw
uh anoxic conditions in the oceans
so the oceans
have this uh these organisms called
phytoplankton
these are
unicellular or
multicellular microorganisms
that have chlorophyll that undergo
photosynthesis
and at least half of the entire planet's
oxygen
is produced by these
phytoplankton organisms that live in the
world's oceans
now if we were to engineer because of
our stupidity an anoxic event in the
oceans which means that the oceans go
they get starved of oxygen
then all of this fight of phytoplankton
will die out
and many other species will die out and
if the oceans die out
we will lose
one of them we will we will lose the
major source of oxygen on the planet and
that could trigger off a catastrophic
chain of events that could wipe out the
majority of the species at least the
terrestrial species of the planet
including humanity because it it would
kill out many of the smaller animals and
plants and that would lead to the
starvation
eventually of of humanity so there are
many mechanisms by which a mass
extinction event can take place
and i am afraid that we are not
currently in a position that we can
survive such a thing
we don't have another planet that we can
go to
because
none of the planets in our solar system
have anything like the conditions we
would need
to survive there and we don't have the
means to send
a significant percentage of humanity to
any of the planets whether it's the moon
whether it's mars whether it's venus
right
so
this is the only home we have the earth
as of today
and if something were to go wrong here i
don't see humanity surviving that so
unfortunately we are currently not in a
position to survive
a mass extinction event if that were to
happen we are in a position to ensure a
mass extinction event does not happen
so we need to get our act together we
need to ensure that we stop polluting
and destroying the oceans we need to
ensure we stop the
deforesting
the terrestrial regions of our planet
we need to stop polluting the atmosphere
if we can do that if we can stop all
this uh
animal agriculture if we can stop people
eating beef
then a great deal we can change a great
deal in the world and maybe ensure that
our future generations will have a
better world to live on and we will
ensure that a mass extinction won't
happen
but it needs to start happening
now or very soon
but otherwise we may not be able to
survive a massive extinction event
srishti says is there any cosmology
branch in india how can a person in
india become a cosmologist
okay so cosmology is a branch of physics
that deals with the
the chronology and the history of the
universe and the uh the physics of the
universe at very large scales the large
scale structure of the universe
and it it combines astronomy and the in
the laws of physics and also sometimes
chemistry etc to understand how the
universe evolved over time and what is
going to be the ultimate
fate of the universe in the very distant
future
so that's what cosmology is about
so how do you become a cosmologist in
india or anywhere else first of all so
to become a cosmologist you need to have
a solid understanding of theoretical
physics physics
you need an understanding of general
relativity of quantum mechanics of
electromagnetism of solid state physics
and various other
allied and associated branches of
physics you need to have a very good
understanding of all these various
branches
of physics so
and i'm not sure if any
universities in india offer courses in
in cosmology but there are certain some
so so what you would need is you would
need
at least a master's degree in physics in
with your specialization in either
quantum physics or nuclear physics
or general relativity
or or quantum physics
or electromagnetism or one of these
closely allied fields in theoretical
physics or maybe solid state physics etc
you would need a master's degree in that
maybe a phd in that and then maybe you
would get
uh
employment in one of the institutes one
of the few institutes in this country in
india
which uh do have some research in
cosmology so i think uh the physical
research laboratory now ahmedabad has
some some research in cosmology may be
happening there tif or mumbai perhaps
and there is a natural national center
for radio astrophysics i think it's a
branch of tifr
pune which does do some astronomical
astrophysical
cosmological research to some extent we
have the raman research institute in
bangalore the indian institute of
science in bangalore
you have ayuka
inter-university consortium or center
for astronomy and astrophysics again in
pune and you have the indian
institute of space science i think it is
in
rivendram
so these are some of the indian
institutions institutes research
institutes that do
some research in cosmology
so that is the path you would have to
take you will need a master's degree and
possibly a phd in one of these
specializations
and then you can apply for a job in one
of these
institutes or institutions and that's
how you would become a cosmologist
if you do want to make a real difference
and do genuine research in cosmology you
will have to go abroad
now you know you know
very well what i feel about this i i
would very much want to see
world-class research being done in india
as of today it is not the case there is
no real
cutting-edge world-class science
research being done in india anywhere
so if you really want to become
a genuine world-class cosmologist and do
some
some real difference
in
research in cosmology you would need to
go to another country maybe in europe
maybe in north america etc
and maybe in the future when india does
get its act together and start
doing genuine research then maybe you
can come back and contribute to the
country but that is in short how you
would become
a cosmologist that is the path you would
follow towards becoming a cosmologist in
india
shreyas says what is a matryoshka brain
so if you know what a matriarchal doll
is it is this nested doll that you have
that is so
uh
typical of russia you have a doll if you
open the door there's another doll
inside you open that doll there's
another third doll inside and you have
dolls all the way in so it's a nested
series of dolls that's called the
matryoshka dal
so a matryoshka brain is a hypothetical
science fiction structure
that
is built on a on a on a
stellar scale so it's essentially a
dyson sphere a dyson sphere is a mega
structure that envelops an entire star
and
it's able to uh
to capture the entire energy output of a
star so that's a dyson sphere so a
matryoshka brain is a computer
in the form of a dyson sphere so you
have a star that is completely enveloped
by this mega structure by this by this
dyson sphere
and the energy output of the star
is utilized
to do computational activity so it is
it is a computer that is larger than a
star now as you know any computer a
laptop or a computer of any kind
it does calculations it needs it does
computations of all kinds it does need a
power source
and it gives off
heat waste heat as a result of all the
computational activities it does
so in the case of a matryoshka brain the
dyson sphere that envelops a star would
use the star's heat and light output as
the energy source it would do
computations
and it would give off
waste heat it would output that out
now a matriarchal brain
is one dyson sphere
and there's another dyson sphere around
it which takes all this waste heat
and uses that as the energy source for
more computation it gives off more waste
heat and there's a third
dyson sphere around it that takes in
this
uh
emitted heat as the energy source and
there's a whole
concentric
series of
dyson spheres that are actually enormous
computers that all use this
output this heat that is output for
computational activity so it is a series
of nested dyson spheres that act as
computers and that is
the comp the concept of a matryoshka
brain so this is a hypothetical
science fiction scenario
we don't know of any
civilization anywhere that is capable of
doing this we have not thus far
encountered any
uh non-human alien civilizations but it
is clear that even if a civilization
were to be sufficiently advanced
it would be able to engineer this sort
of a structure it is certainly possible
it is not impossible the laws of physics
don't
uh
preclude
this sort of a machine from being
constructed but it is well beyond the
capability of the human species but it
is certainly possible theoretically
hypothetically
dominic says is it possible to make a
spacecraft that uses the plentiful
hydrogen available in outer space
so that's a concept that has been again
discussed
in uh
science fiction
it's called a bassard ramjet
so in a bassar drum ramjet
you would have a
spacecraft with a fusion engine
it fuses hydrogen and this fusion
reaction
impels it forward
and in front of the spacecraft there is
this enormous ram scoop
which is a scoop that's made up of
enormous magnetic fields
that go out into space for thousands of
kilometers maybe millions of kilometers
now we know that the interstellar medium
is full of this very diffuse
hydrogen gas it's extremely diffuse
and this intercell intercellular medium
is a better vacuum a more perfect vacuum
than anything we can have
on the planet earth and yet it does have
hydrogen atoms it is a very low density
of hydrogen atoms and perhaps even
molecules in some places
so
a bassad ram ramjet would
exploit this
property of the interstellar space
so the spacecraft would be propelled by
a fusion reaction and it would have this
enormous ram scoop in front of it
magnetic fields that extend for
thousands or millions of kilometers and
these magnetic fields suck in all this
diffuse hydrogen gas and they are they
bring it all into the
into the input of the
of the fusion engine
of the ramjet
and that's what serves as the fuel for
this enormous
enormous ramjet
engine
so yes it is definitely
possible if you have the technological
means to create such a machine
to use the interstellar hydrogen
for fuel in
in a spacecraft it is definitely
possible but of course once again we
still are we don't have anything close
to that sort of technological ability as
of today maybe a thousand years in the
future if we
last that long then maybe we may be able
to
build such a
such a spacecraft
akash says does the dark matter hello if
it exists envelope the galaxies and also
permeate them
also are we inside
this dark matter hello
so
uh
we know the dark matter hellos do exist
we have observed them uh we just
discussed the
galactic rotation curves which is one of
the signature
one one of the
phenomena
that tell us that these dark matter
halos do exist so a galactic dark matter
hello is typically spherical
in shape we know that galaxies are
pancake shaped most of them especially
spiral galaxies like the milky way and
the andromeda galaxy
but the dark matter hello which we can't
see but whose gravitational effects we
do observe
these halos are spherical
in shape and for the milky way the dark
matte dark matter hello at the diameter
of about 2 million
two million light years
it's a spherical hello and the dark
matter is not only found in the exterior
part of the galaxy it is everywhere it
is all around us
it is everywhere we are currently
inside
the dark matter hello it is in this room
where i am right now wherever you are
sitting and watching this it is
in your room as well it is passing right
through you but you don't feel it
so that is what dark matter is it is
some
it is an unknown particle or substance
which interacts only gravitationally and
the gravitational interaction is so
incredibly weak
that we can't perceive it
especially when it comes to very small
particles
yeah
so that is what it is we are in it we
are bathed in dark matter particles
but we have no idea what they are so it
is right here right here at this very
moment
i am sitting in an entire ocean
of dark matter particles the sun
is inside a notion of dark matter
particles our milk our milky way our our
solar system it's passing through a wind
of dark matter
and that's what it is
dungar singh johan says what is the
shape of a black hole can we see the
back side of a black hole
so when it comes to black holes when we
talk about the shape of a black hole we
are talking about the shape of the event
horizon of a black hole which is the
boundary of no return
so once a light particle a photon
crosses the event horizon it never comes
back it is not
able capable of coming back that is just
the way it is so the shape of a black
hole is the shape of the event horizon
of the black hole
so for a non-rotating black hole
which is also called a schwarzschild
black hole the shape is perfectly
spherical it's a perfect sphere
in the case of a schwarzschild
non-rotating black hole
but for rotating black holes the shape
of the event horizon horizon is oblate
it's like a squashed sphere
so on the poles of the sphere
the poles are the the essentially the
axis around which the black hole is
rotating so around the poles the black
hole is slightly squashed and around the
equatorial region of the black hole it
is slightly
uh
elongated so it's like a squashed sphere
in the case of a rotating black hole
now can we see the the back side of a
black hole well a black a black hole has
no uh there's nothing to see in it it's
completely dark it's completely you
could say transparent
no light ever comes out of it so you
cannot really see the back side of a
black hole or any side of it but what
you can see
is light that is behind the black hole
so recently this uh phenomenon was
observed that light actually went all
the way around around the black hole and
we were able to see it again
so an object which is behind the black
hole we may be we may be able to see it
because of
this phenomenon
in which light it's uh the space time
itself is warped and bend and light
curves
because of this phenomenon right
it's called lensing gravitational
lensing so let's say i am sitting here i
have a black hole
in front of me and there is a star
exactly behind precisely behind
me behind the black hole so which means
that the black hole is exactly between
me and the star then i will be able to
observe the light of the star which
comes behind the black hole it just
curves around the black hole
so that is what we do indeed see but we
cannot see anything about the black hole
itself because it is completely and
perfectly well almost perfectly dark
there is the phenomenon of hawking
radiation which is a completely
different thing so we don't get to see
any features of the black hole or
anything but we do see a flux of
radiation that comes out of it which is
a separate phenomenon
pink line cabs says
will
automation destroy or save humanity
well automation is a a bunch of
technologies robotics artificial
intelligence machine learning
so you have software automation you have
algorithmic automation you have actual
physical automation done by assembly
line robots other kinds of robots and so
on and so forth right
so automation is a tool
and tools can be used in a variety of
ways you can use a tool for something
good you can use a tool for something
bad it all depends on who is the person
or the organization or the entity
that
holds the tool in their hand
right
so
today if you look at the world who runs
the world it is the western countries
that essentially run the world
it is these big capitalistic
corporations who run the world and the
entire objective of the global system
today
is
to make money
it's all about that it's it's the system
that has been placed since in place
since the days of
the colonization of the world by the
european countries
it's a system that has been placed
that has been in place since the days of
the east india company
it's all about amassing money
and the better tools you have the better
you are at amassing money so today
artificial intelligence
machine learning robotics it is all
being
developed by various corporations and
various powerful governments who have
all the money
and they are using it to amass more
resources and more power and more
influence for themselves
so as of today
automation
is going to make a small number of
countries
and a small number of individuals and a
small number of corporations incredibly
insanely rich
and it's going to happen at the expense
of the rest of the world
and that's why there is this arms race
of assault going on
technological race
in which technology is the new arms
right
so automation is one part of that
so it's all about how you use it and
today the people who are using who who
are developing these these automation
tools
they are doing it for the purpose of
enriching and empowering themselves not
for the benefit of humanity today we
already have enough money and enough
resources to end world hunger
once and for all we have enough money
enough resources to ensure that
everybody has good standards of living
all across the world and yet you have so
much disparity so much inequality it's
because all of the wealth has been
stolen and amassed by the western world
and now they're using various other
tools
such as automation
and other technologies to enrich
themselves even more this is a new kind
of colonization so as we stand today
automation
is going to
well it's not going to save humanity
it's going to make the rich richer and
the poor
poorer is going to make the powerful
even more powerful and it's going to
disempower everybody else
so that is the direction in which we are
going and that's why i keep saying india
needs to rise and and it's it needs to
rise on its own terms today india is a
second rate knockoff of the west
that's what india aspires to be that's
what india's leaders aspire india to to
look like in the future an
english-speaking second-rate
a cut price copy
of the western model of the western
world india does not india should not go
in the direction india needs to rise
again as a civilization on the basis of
its own
cultural and civilizational values only
then
will we have an alternative model
to the model that we have today which is
the model that even the chinese
are copying
so that's what needs to happen
avinash says what is the meaning of
baryonic
matter that's a good question
so what is a baryon
so see
baryons are sub atomic particles that
are made up of odd number of quarks
so you have six quarks you have the up
quark the down quark the charm clock the
strange quark
the top quark and the bottom quark and
these quarks have fractional charges the
up quark
charm clock and the top quark have plus
two thirds elementary charge
and the down quark the strange cork and
the bottom quark have minus one third
elementary charge
these are the most fundamental particles
that we know of these six quarks
and baryons
are particles that are made up of
an odd number
of quarks at least three quarks
so for example you have the proton which
has uud one up quark another up quark
and a down quark in a
in a bound state
so the proton is a bound state of two up
quarks and one down quark it has a
positive one charge the neutron is a
bound state of one up quark and two down
quarks so these are triplets of quarks
and these are what are known as baryons
right you also have
exotic baryons penta quarks
which have been observed so these are
bound states of five quarks so as long
as you have a bound state of three or
more quarks and it is an
odd number of quarks that is what is
known as a baryon you also have mesons
mesons are bosons they have they are
bound states of even number of quarks
so that's how it goes so baryonic matter
is essentially matter that's made up of
protons and neutrons so most of the
matter that we see around us that we
experience in the world is baryonic
matter you also have leptons there are
electrons and neutrinos and various
other kinds of particles
in this submatter in the subatomic
particle zoo but that's what baryonic
matter is is
it is matter that of that uh
that follows
uh fermi dirac statistics these are
fermions as opposed to bosons which
obey bose-einstein statistics so that in
a nutshell in very brief is what
baryonic matter is
dungar singh johann says is there
anything non-physical in existence if
yes then what would be its definition
can we perceive it through our logic and
senses
see this is a question about that that
transcends the physical world and goes
into the philosophical world
so what can we perceive through our
senses
we can perceive
physical things
through our senses
our senses are all predicated on mostly
electromagnetism
which is how we perceive light and color
and all that we perceive sound through
the vibrations
of the air
acoustic vibrations of air
and we perceive things like shape and
and hardness and all that because of
well because of quantum mechanics
because of the laws of quantum mechanics
so these are the reasons why we perceive
what we perceive and this this is all
physical
now we do know that we are conscious
we do
perceive
something called consciousness but we
don't know how to define it and we don't
know if it is an emergent phenomenon or
it is something else entirely
we don't have the
foggiest idea of what that is
so is consciousness physical or
non-physical is it something we imagine
or does it is does it really exist
these questions are still
well unanswered
so that is the only non-physical thing
that we if it is non-physical that we
may be able to perceive maybe it itself
is something that emerges out of
out of uh
ordered complexity perhaps we don't know
this is all speculation
now
what is the definition of something that
is non-physical
something that is non-physical is
something that is not observable
it is either an object that is
non-observable or a phenomenon that is
not observable
for example
uh the soul
the soul is something that has never
been observed you can't measure it you
can't quantify it you don't know its
shape with size its color its weight or
anything like that
it is something that people believe in
but it has never been observed
scientifically unambiguously or even
ambiguously it's never been observed so
that is something that is non-physical
does it exist well
as a scientist i have never seen any
evidence of it existing do i believe in
it well that's entirely personal to me
many scientists may believe in the
existence of a soul or of a god or gods
or whatever
but in the physical world we cannot
observe measure quantify
these non-physical things so do these
things exist do non-physical entities
objects phenomena exist we cannot
observe them
and therefore we cannot say we cannot
say for sure whether they exist or not
as a pure
from a purely scientific person
perspective
what is non-observable what is
non-measurable what is non-quantifiable
does not exist
and science is limited to the observable
universe
it doesn't mean
that certain things may not exist
because
our understanding of science is very
very rudimentary our instruments our
senses are very rudimentary very
primitive
and therefore if our instruments
if our scientific instruments if our
senses were to progress further then we
may be be able to to observe certain
things that we currently consider to be
non-physical
but as of today
none of the non-physical things
is observable
such as the soul
or god or gods
or spirits or whatever you call it we
cannot observe it and therefore we
cannot say that it exists we cannot
claim
without evidence that it exists we
cannot perceive it through our senses or
through logic
but it doesn't mean it doesn't exist
okay so that's that's my position on
that
okay mayuri says while the dinosaurs
were here for 270 million years they did
not care about the sun or the stars
we on the other hand in our short seven
million years have reached the moons the
moon and mars
so which of the following statements is
right a we are nothing but a tiny speck
of dust in the vast universe
and b
the universe has meaning because there
is something us
to observe it
well that's again a philosophical
question
um
the dinosaurs were here for yeah some
few hundred million years
well we don't know whether
they cared or not about the sun or the
stars we don't know
maybe there were certain reasonably
intelligent dinosaurs who liked to look
at the stars
and look at the sun and they were aware
or conscious of the existence of the sun
and the stars on the moon
we don't know
we cannot assume that there were no
reasonably intelligent dinosaurs i'm
sure there were certain dinosaurs that
were as intelligent as our dogs or the
dolphins or elephants it's entirely
possible
so
maybe some of them did care did observe
and did perceive these things
now we as humans
have existed for about
maybe two million years
two three million years
homo sapiens as our species has existed
for about 250 000 years
now we have indeed reached the moon we
have sent spacecraft to mars
and to other places
so which of these following statements
we are indeed
a very small speck of dust in the vast
universe we know that the observable
universe has a
radius or diameter is it 90
billion light years i think it's the
diameter
so we are clearly insignificant in
comparison with the size of the
observable universe the actual universe
may even
dwarf what we see of the universe
so if you look at the size of the solar
system if you look at the size of the
earth it's clearly an insignificant tiny
speck of dust that there is no question
about it it is indeed true
there may be many more
uh advanced
species
of of beings out there in the universe
that we have not yet observed
so we are clearly insignificant we are
clearly very small in significant
insignificant tiny all that
uh question b is does the universe have
meaning because there is something else
to observe it well
that again is is about the observer
effect
something doesn't exist unless it is
observed einstein once said that does it
mean that the moon doesn't exist if i
don't look at it
so again this is a philosophical
question we don't really know the answer
uh i remember when i was a little kid i
used to wonder if i'm not looking at
something does it really exist
and then i would quickly turn around and
look and yeah it's there
but does it exist when i'm not looking
that was
the question that i
had
when i was a kid
and that
it turns out it's one of fundamental
questions i mean does the universe exist
if we are not observing it there are
certain parts of the universe that may
never have been observed by humans
so does it mean that for all intents and
purposes those parts of the universe
don't exist
these are some very fundamental
questions that arise out of our study of
the ultra microscopic world quantum
mechanics
so maybe
maybe there's a possibility that
that
reality
is meaningful only when
something is observing it and what is
that something
is it an intelligent observer is it a
consciousness
so these questions
we don't really have an answer to them
as of today
these are the deep mysteries that we are
currently
wrestling with
in our our
study
of this extremely mysterious field of
physics quantum physics quantum field
theory quantum mechanics especially the
interpretation
of quantum mechanics
because it does
throw up extremely
strange and
rather uncomfortable
paradoxes at us
so
i would say that we are to to answer the
two questions in short we are indeed
nothing but a tiny speck of dust in the
whole universe
and
the second question we don't really know
maybe the universe does exist without
any
observer observing it or maybe it does
take an observer
to observe the universe to bring it into
existence which then makes us ask this
big question that a wave function
doesn't collapse
into reality
unless it is observed by an external
observer
now our universe itself has one wave
function and we know the universe exists
so which external observer is observing
the universe
that's the question right
so yeah it it throws up all kinds of
mysteries and paradoxes and things that
kind of transcend
science and physics
and we currently don't have answers to
this
akash says there were so many different
types of human species why did only homo
sapiens
survive that's a good question
so
see homo sapiens as a species is is a
very recent species it's about 250
000 years old a quarter of a million
years old the most successful
species of human that we know of is homo
erectus
so the oldest
fossilized specimens of homo erectus
are found in africa that's about 2
million years old
we know that
there is evidence that homo erectus
made its way into asia about 1.7 million
years before today
and the last
known existence of homo erectus is
about 100 000 years before today in
indonesia so it seems to have died out
as a species only one lakh years before
today
so so homo erectus is the most
successful
human species of all time it lasted
almost 2
million years almost
and compared to that we are very recent
just a quarter of a million years old
right
so there have been many types of human
species
now did only homo sapiens survive is the
question
we know that there have been other
subspecies of humans like the
neanderthals
that were alive until about 20 30 000
years ago
we know that the denisovans also existed
a different subspecies of humans
we had the
homo florences from indonesia we had
uh
homo erectus and so on
we also know
that
we carry
about four percent
neanderthal dna
which means that we have neanderthal
ancestors it's like having one great
grandparent or
something like that
one great one great great grandparent
who was a neanderthal or maybe one great
grandparent the math is very simple
so we do have neanderthal dna
we have
had neanderthal ancestors which means
that they haven't really died out in
entirely
their and their descendants are still
alive that is us
so it's clear that homospacious is
sapience is not a pure species
it is a mixed species
we have neanderthal dna some of us also
have denisovan dna
so again it means that they don't
denisons did not die out entirely their
descendants are still alive
then that is us
and there is another
ghost
dna ghost population whose dna
exists within us
and that population that species or
subspecies
has not been identified
and that could very well
be the great homo erectus
so
what i mean to say is that there is no
such thing as a pure species
there is no such thing as a pure
um
yeah no no pure species right
so
it is incorrect to say that the
neanderthals died out entirely it is
incorrect to say that denisovans died
out entirely or maybe even though the
the homo erectus also still survives
in some way in some form through us so
we are the sum total of a great number
of different species that interbred
together
there may be many other
unknown
populations whose dna we are still
carrying
right
so we are the we are the only ones that
have survived till now
maybe it's because we are the most
recent one
and maybe we are the ones who adapted
the best in the past 100
000 years or so
so we don't exactly know why we are the
only ones who survive did we
ensure that the neanderthals were wiped
out did was there a conflict between the
homo sapiens and the near the
neanderthals
that is something that has been
speculated but we don't have complete
evidence of that we do have evidence of
inbreeding interbreeding between us and
them
and same for the daily so once and so on
so on so it is most likely that
homo sapiens was the most adaptable in
the past quarter of a million years and
that's why we have survived and maybe we
were the most intelligent intelligent
ones
and we interpret with these other
species we absorbed their best traits
their best dna traits and that's what we
carry with us today
so that isn't brief about this question
avinash says is is dark energy negative
energy
well dark energy is an unknown form of
it is not negative it is definitely
positive energy
it does produce some kind of repulsive
force effect
it
produces the it it
causes
it seems to cause the
accelerating expansion of the universe
so that's all we know about it it's one
of the most mysterious things that we
know of in the universe
it makes up more than 80 percent more
than 73 percent of the
of the mass energy
composition of the universe
and we don't have the least idea of what
it is so it's a it's an extremely
mysterious thing but what we know is
that it is not negative energy it is not
that it is positive
energy
mass energy whatever you call it it's
not negative energy but that's all we
can say about it as of today it's one of
the greatest
mysteries
in existence
ishwar mudi says which is a better fuel
for of the future according to you solar
electric nuclear or hydrogen
so solar fuel nuclear fuel hydrogen they
all have uh
well they all have good prospects
it all depends on the context
so nuclear fuel is is uh
it's very energetic it it
it gives you a great deal of energy
output for
from a very little amount of fuel so
that's a good thing
and if you can use it the right way it
it can maybe have almost
no it may not cause any pollution if you
know how to dispose of whatever is left
behind
and in the future we may be able to use
uh
materials
such as helium-3 which is found in
abundance in the lunar regolith in the
soil of the moon so that could power
future fusion reactors and fusion
reactors are
they will be extremely fuel efficient
and there will be almost no
byproducts you know waste products from
that so that is a very good future fuel
so it has good prospects for the future
for sure
solar energy if you can learn how to
harness it more efficiently
is also a very good prospect for the
future
hydrogen is found in abundance in the
interstellar medium so in the future if
someday we are able to travel across
interstellar distances then that could
be a very good source of fuel especially
in this in the
context of what we discussed earlier the
the basard ramjet kind of engine
so yeah so all three of them
have different applications depending on
on what context
we are in if we are to be an earthbound
species the nuclear fuel nuclear energy
makes a lot of sense especially if you
are able to
build
fusion reactors
if we can use uh helium-3 for instance
that's a great source of energy
solar energy also is also great if we
are
within the solar system especially close
to the sun
and hydrogen makes sense if you're
traveling interstellar distances so all
three have
good future prospects depending on the
context
in which they are being used
shivans shivanch says can you please
speak about asteroid mining
and resource extraction what are the
potential problems in this process
and what are all the feasible methods by
which we can do it
and does it have the potential to create
another benchmark in the history of
wealthy people so in the future i have
spoken about how
asteroid mining can potentially possibly
create
trillionaires in the future because
there is so much
so much mineral resources etc that one
can extract from asteroids now here is a
reality check
see the asteroids the vast majority of
asteroids are small
the shape of a small rock or maybe tens
of meters in diameter that's quite small
and the amount of minerals you can
extract from an asteroid that is maybe
100 meters in diameter is just a few
grams maybe a few grams of cobalt maybe
a few grams of gold or aluminum
so
an asteroid which is about 100 meters in
diameter is not that good of
of a of an investment to go all the way
there and to extract
and to try and extract minerals or
resources from it
now the other thing is that the average
distance
between any two asteroids
is about a million kilometers
which is more than double the distance
between the earth and the moon
so
if you go to one asteroid and you
check it out
and you discover that it doesn't have
too many minerals in it it's not mineral
rich
then to go to the next asteroid
would be at least a million kilometers
away
so you would need to spend that much
fuel to go all the way there and then
try the other asteroid and see whether
it has any resources or not
so it is not an efficient process
the asteroids are so
they are so far away from each other
and most of them are so small
that they are not a valuable
investment
for you to spend so much money and
resources going all the way to the
asteroid belt
and
going to one asteroid and we don't know
which asteroid contains what minerals
there is no price tag on an asteroid
that this asteroid contains these many
metric tons of of material and these
minute tons of gold or cobalt or
aluminum inside it there's no way of
knowing unless you actually go there
and do some prospecting
and even if you find a large asteroid
with a significant amount of some
mineral that you need
how are you going to extract it
you cannot do extraction in space right
extraction is done in in refineries
on earth
you have iron refineries or other
refineries of other things of other
materials or minerals
so there's an entire process that you
have to create an entire factory that
you have to set up
you to first grind the material
then put it through various chemical
processing maybe some heat treatment and
so on it's a it's a multi-stage process
you just can't do it in space
so it is actually extremely impractical
and unfeasible
to do any kind of asteroid mining with
with anything close to the kind of
technology we have today so it may not
be possible for the next hundred years
or maybe even the next thousand years
unless we can
find ways of knowing from far away which
asteroid
contains how much
mineral or whatever substance we are
seeking and then we may be able to
target those but as of today it is
extremely
unfeasible
to even think of asteroid mining so it
is not something that's going to be
possible in the next century it's not
going to create trillionaires anytime
soon
it is still very much
in the realm of science fiction
ashna says what's your take on light
pollution yeah light pollution is
something that most people are not aware
of so just 20 30 years ago the skies
were very dark across the world
but today if you see
most cities most urban centers most
towns there is so much light that you
can't see anything in the sky in the
night
there are you can see barely a handful
of stars
in the night
in the past like 30 years ago 40 years
ago you could see the entire milky way
in the night even in small towns even in
cities at night
because there was so so little light
pollution so light pollution essentially
is that we are
that
we have so much light now on the surface
of the planet that it goes up into the
sky
and because of the
kind of gases we have in the atmosphere
either small smoke or pollution or even
the the
clouds
so all of this light is reflected in the
atmosphere the entire atmosphere glows
and because of that it is impossible
to do any
astronomy or to do any any
star gazing or anything like that so
that is light pollution there is so much
light glow in the sky at night that you
can't see any stars anymore you can
barely see a handful of stars and that
is something that is impacting a lot of
things not just star gazers and
astronomers it is impacting the
circadian rhythm rhythms of people
it is impacting the circadian cycles of
other species of birds of animals
because it all the the circadian cycle
of animals and
and birds and insects depends on the
fact that the night sky is supposed to
be dark and only
for a few hours of the day you have
light
from the sun
so it is messing up the circadian cycles
of non-human species it is even messing
up the life cycles of plants and trees
so it is going to have long-term effects
and it is something that hopefully
should be combated
so what needs to be done is that our
light
sources need to become more efficient we
are wasting too much of our light just
throwing it up into the into the
atmosphere
what we need to do is to we need to
ensure that all of it falls only on the
ground and doesn't
uh
get wasted so it not only causes light
pollution it is also a wastage of energy
so that is the situation we are in there
is a great deal of light pollution we
can actually see the entire
uh state of the planet from from space
at night we can see the entire planet
lit up
you know
the you can see the various towns and
cities you can see the whole country of
india from space it is so bright at
night
so that is all light pollution and that
is
an enormous wastage
of energy we need to become more energy
efficient
and if we do that we will also be able
to
reverse this effect of light pollution
says do you think that hackers will be
the future
soldiers of a country
they are already soldiers hackers
because hacking is one of the major
domains the cyber domain is one of the
major domains of warfare nowadays
so using uh computer hacking using cyber
techniques you can
even
countries overnight you can cause
traffic jams you can cause
disruptions in traffic you can
uh
halt stock exchanges you can cause
electrical grids to collapse you can
cause blackouts power power outages
and whatnot you can stop the entire
communications of a country all your
phones will go dead your internet will
disappear it can cause chaos overnight
and today many countries already do have
the capability of doing this
and certain trial runs may actually be
happening from time to time in various
parts of the world
so yes
hackers will indeed be
they are indeed considered to be
soldiers
for example the
chinese army the so-called people's
liberation army has a
cyber division so those are all military
officers those hackers you know
so yeah it's already part of the
military domain
and so are other domains as well but yes
hackers are indeed
soldiers they can be considered to be
soldiers
avinash asks how will the universe end
so there are a number of theories of
what will happen the the
long-term
fate of the universe
uh one possibility is that the the
universe started in a big bang
and it will die in a big grip which
means the universe will keep on
expanding forever
and eventually all sources of light
energy heat will dissipate away
and the universe will become a cold
lifeless place and it will just go on
expanding forever and eventually
everything will just rip apart dark
energy will increase so much that even
atoms and molecules will be broken up
and that is how the universe will end
that is one theory the other theory is
that the universe will expand for some
time and then it will contract again
and you will have a big crunch
so
it will be a big bang in reverse
everything will contract into itself
one theory is that there will be a big
bounce
the universe will expand for some time
then it will contract again
and uh
according to loop quantum gravity it
will not contract into a similar
singularity but it will contract into
a
volume of space that is 10 raised to
minus 99 cubic meters
in volume and it will bounce bounce back
from that again and you will have
another big bang kind of event from
there so it's kind of a cyclical uh
model of the universe
then according to roger penrose's
conformal cyclic universe theory
uh
the long large
the eventual end of the universe will
it will exp it will keep on expanding
and that will in turn be the same as a
new big bang kind of event so there are
a number of theories that we have
but we
we the kind of data that we have is
woefully insufficient
we have been around for a very small
time on the universe and we know very
little about it
we understand less than five percent of
the universe so all we have is theories
and hypotheses
so we have these different models of
what could be the eventual long-term
fate of the universe
but these are only theories we don't
know for sure
so that's where we are as of today
manab says do aliens live among us and
if yes are they a threat to humanity
well
we should at least have one question
about aliens right it's not fun until we
have one question about aliens at least
so do aliens live amongst us we don't
have any evidence that aliens live
amongst us
we have no evidence of any other alien
civilization anywhere else
in the known universe
and we have no evidence that any of them
live amongst us it's always nice to
imagine it makes the world a very
interesting place if there are hidden
aliens living amongst us
so
it's nice to imagine that but and many
people have claimed that
that aliens actually exist they are here
amongst us there are claims about this
there are claims of ufos coming and
visiting us there are claims that crop
circles are created by aliens
there are these uh ancient aliens
theorists whatever that is and there are
other scientists
and people with reasonably good
reputations who claim that aliens do
exist
but where's the evidence
evidence has to be presented evidence
has to be unambiguous
it has to be incontrovertible evidence
when you have a lawsuit for example
evidence has to be presented in court
evidence that stands up to scrutiny
somebody makes a claim that does not
constitute evidence
so as of today we don't have evidence
that proves
beyond any doubt
that aliens exist that ufos exist and
that aliens
live amongst us and therefore from
from the lack of evidence one would have
to say
that it does not appear
that there is no credible
or sufficient evidence
that aliens exist among us
or
so so if they don't exist among us
we have no idea whether they're a threat
to humanity or not
so
that's the answer we we don't have any
credible unambiguous evidence that
aliens exist or
live amongst
us okay that brings me to an end of
these questions
let me take some live questions do you
have any live questions ask me now
okay let me see do you guys have any
questions
harshit says area 51 is a tourist
destination of aliens well that's what
they say it's it's it's become a tourist
spot you know
people go there and there are these
signs signboards etc with alien faces on
them and you go there and you take
pictures with that take selfies
and so on and so forth some people camp
out at night outside this area 51 beyond
the boundary
and they
try and do some ufo spotting
but so far there's been no real evidence
you know
that these ufos exist
amir khan is an alien well
show me the proof he does look like an
alien but
we don't approve of that
they even said michael jackson and some
other prominent people are aliens but
well where's the proof
it's it's nice it's humorous but well
it's it's only that isn't it it's only
humor
uh kapil says what will be the source of
energy once humans achieve type three
civilization status
a type three a kardashian type three
civilization so what's a type 1
civilization it's a civilization that is
able to control
all the resources of its home planet
type 2 means you're able to control the
resources of your
home
solar system
and type 3 means you're able to control
the entire resources of your home galaxy
so i would say that if humans can
achieve type 3 status
it means that we would be able to build
a dyson sphere around an entire galaxy
so the light heat output of the entire
galaxy would be the
source of energy
of a type 3
civilization
okay do we have other questions
uh galaxies look stationary then why do
scientists say
that they rotate i think i've answered
this question before but let me
take it again
so there is something called redshift
and blueshift it's the doppler effect
when it is applied to light
so in the doppler effect when a train is
coming towards you and it is blowing its
horn or vessel
you hear a very high pitched sound but
the moment it passes you the sound the
the frequency of the sound changes it
becomes lower in pitch so that is a
doppler effect when applied to
sound waves now the same phenomenon is
applied it also exists in light waves
so when a light source is coming towards
you its frequencies are its wavelength
is compressed and it is its frequencies
look uh its colors look bluer
so all the frequencies are shifted
towards the blue end of the spectrum
that is called blue shift and when a
light source is moving away from you
its
frequencies are all red shifted so when
you see a galaxy
which is uh in the same plane as you
and when when one end of the galaxy is
observed one finds that it is either red
shifted or blue shifted if one end is
blue shifted you find the other end is
red shifted or if you find this end is
red shifted or blue shifted the other
one
is redshifted so you always find that
one end of the galaxy the light so the
the light that comes from it
is shifted towards the blue end of the
spectrum
and the other end is shifted towards the
right towards the red end of the
spectrum so that tells you that one end
of the galaxy is coming towards you the
other one is going away from you and
that is unmistakable evidence of
galactic rotation so that is one of the
best ways of of of seeing for yourself
that galaxies do rotate and that's how
we know
that galaxies rotate
how to become a physicist and historian
like you well it takes
many many years it takes decades you
have to study a lot read a lot
in the case of physics you have to start
with learning mathematics
you have to learn really advanced
mathematics to understand physics
so if you if you
put in the hours and if you put in the
years in learning mathematics then
physics becomes incredibly easy
because
mathematics is the language of physics
and when it comes to history well
i have learned history by by reading
hundreds of books and thousands of
articles research papers etc
it's it's it takes years it takes
decades it's not an easy thing to do
okay some more question
sakit says is our country a secret
superpower well if it's a secret it's a
secret we don't know about it
from what i see from what i observe
india is not anywhere close to being a
superpower maybe we are developing some
some capabilities right now
technological scientific etc military
capabilities and so on perhaps we may be
doing it in secret
it is always best to develop such
capabilities in secret don't tell the
world about it
if it is being done i would be very
happy about it nobody would be happier
than me if we are doing that
but from what we see from what is known
in the open we are not close to being a
superpower or even a regional power
the kind of uh
statements
our
foreign ministry makes et cetera is that
we are aspiring to be a regional power
so
so that tells you where we are today of
course you must conceal your
capabilities
you must bide your time and hide your
capabilities if you are serious about
being a great power
so i
very much hope it is being done but if
it is a secret we are not meant to know
it
so
so as of today we are not a superpower
maybe we are trying to become a secret
superpower which would be a good thing
but i don't see any evidence of that and
maybe with good reason
okay some more questions maybe one more
question
how do you remember many historical
events and other information
well if you're curious if you're
interested you remember things
when you go and watch a movie which you
find very interesting don't you remember
everything every last detail
so if you have the curiosity about it
you will remember things and the more
you you read
about history the more connections you
make inside your subconscious mind about
various events that seem to be very far
apart so the more you read the more you
study the more connections you make the
more patterns you see and that's how you
remember things and i don't try to
memorize dates
i know in which century something
happened or maybe in which decade
something happened but most likely most
usually i don't remember the exact dates
it is pointless to try and memorize
dates because then you are distracting
you you are
you are not focusing on what's more
important which is causality cause and
effect
so what's more important is to
understand why things happen and what
are the forces that make things happen
historical events
right not what date what happened but
unfortunately in our in education system
all we have to do is memorize dates
which is a painful thing and it doesn't
really give you any understanding of why
things happen and why
and what forces
shape
the events of the world
okay okay one more question
we are going towards geopolitics this is
supposed to be science
is our galaxy rotating around something
well our galaxy is rotating
around
its center of mass
around the center of the galaxy
and the center of the galaxy is a
supermassive black hole which is i think
several
million
solar masses
in in mass
so that is what it is revolving around
around is it orbiting around something
we are not very sure we have a local
super cluster the virgo supercluster
which is a
collection a local collection of
galaxies
several hundred or maybe several
thousand galaxies so that is what it is
but
it we don't know for sure if this
collection or cluster of galaxies is
orbiting something else we don't know
for sure
okay one more question i will take one
final question
do you think neanderthals who are sort
of extinct now
had a role in indian history is it
possible they could be wander cena
as they looked more like apes
i don't know
see um
they seem to have gone extinct as a
distinct species
about 20 or 30 000 years ago
that is the best evidence that we have
now i don't know of any evidence of
neanderthals
in india
because we don't do any archaeology we
don't do anything so
even if the evidence exists somewhere in
india that they may have lived in india
at some point in time we have not found
it
and therefore in the absence of any
evidence of fossilized remains or other
other remains
or artifacts of the neanderthals
in the absence of any such evidence from
india we cannot say for sure
whether they lived in india and if they
did live until what time were they alive
in india we can't say
so in the absence of any form of
evidence about it we cannot speculate
about whether they have been
part of the wanderer cena because they
look like hips we don't know
we will know only if we have some
evidence
and we don't even know when the ramayana
happened when those events happened it's
clearly several thousand years before
today
maybe the the rama setup can give us
some clues if our government will go and
then do some dating activity there then
we may know
when this uh structure was constructed
but as of today it's too unambiguous we
have very little data
so we can't say
so unfortunately we don't have the
answer to this question it's a good
question
but we don't have an answer to it as of
today
okay my friends uh this brings us to an
end of this session thank you so much
for all your questions
thank you very much and i will see you
in the next episode i will see you very
soon until then take care thank you very
much
and have a good day have a good night
bye